{"tossups": [{"question": "A satirical work of this type by Ambrose Bierce claims that the French eat more bread than anyone else because \"only they know how to make [wheat] palatable.\" An American work of this type used twenty-six languages to establish etymologies, and was written by Noah (*) Webster. Lexicographers create, For ten points, what books that provide the pronunciations and definitions of words?", "answer": "dictionary (accept dictionaries)", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>dictionary</u></b>", "acceptable": ["dictionary", "dictionary"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept dictionaries"}, {"question": "This civilization\u2019s thinkers developed a belief in material monism, the idea that all objects in the world are made of a single \u201cfirst element.\u201d One such thinker from this civilization, (*) Anaximenes [ah-nax-ih-men-ees], believed that that element was air; another thinker, Thales [thay-lees], believed it was water. For ten points, name this civilization whose natural philosophers from Miletus inspired its later schools, such as the Lyceum of\r\nAristotle in Athens.", "answer": "ancient Greece (accept Miletus until it is read, but do not accept other specific Greek city-states)", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>ancient Greece</u></b>", "acceptable": ["ancient Greece", "ancient Greece"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Miletus until it is read, but do not accept other specific Greek city-states"}, {"question": "One of these devices, named for Chandrasekhar, detected X-rays from Sagittarius A* \ufffc in 2000 after being deployed by the (*) Columbia shuttle. One of these devices, named for James Webb, will be launched into space in 2018. For ten points, name these astronomical instruments deployed in space and used for seeing long distances, such as the Hubble.", "answer": "space telescopes (accept space observatorys; accept descriptive answers, like telescopes in orbit or satellite telescopes) \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc[A- star] \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>space telescopes \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc</u></b> [A- star]", "acceptable": ["space telescopes \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc", "space telescopes \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept space observatorys; accept descriptive answers, like telescopes in orbit or satellite telescopes"}, {"question": "During this battle, Simon Fraser was targeted for death by Benedict Arnold, whose wounded leg was memorialized at Bemis Heights, in this battle's location. John Burgoyne's (*) surrender at this 1777 battle led France to promise aid to the colonies. For ten points, name this upstate New York battle in which victory over the British is often cited as the turning point of the American Revolution.", "answer": "Battle(s) of Saratoga (accept the Battle of Bemis Heights before it is read; accept \"Campaign\" or similar terms in place of \"Battle\")", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Saratoga (accept the Battle of Bemis Heights before it is read; accept \"Campaign\" or similar terms in place of \"Battle\")</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Saratoga (accept the Battle of Bemis Heights before it is read; accept \"Campaign\" or similar terms in place of \"Battle\")", "Battle of Saratoga (accept the Battle of Bemis Heights before it is read; accept \"Campaign\" or similar terms in place of \"Battle\")"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "s"}, {"question": "A Symbolist composer in this country never wrote opera again after his work about Pelleas and Melisande flopped. After visiting this country, George Gershwin wrote a piece for orchestra, saxophone, and car horns about \"An American in\" this city. A conservatory in this country twice expelled (*) Maurice Ravel for continually failing to win its competitions. For ten points, name this home country of Claude Debussy and the Paris Conservatory.", "answer": "France", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>France</u></b>", "acceptable": ["France", "France"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This organ's duct of Wirsung drains through the ampulla of Vater into the duodenum. Like the stomach and intestines, this organ can develop gastrinomas. Amylin and glucagon are produced by beta and alpha cells in this organ's (*) Islets of Langerhans, which helps promote stability of blood glucose levels. Type I diabetes targets, for ten points, what organ's insulin-secreting cells?", "answer": "pancreas", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>pancreas</u></b>", "acceptable": ["pancreas", "pancreas"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This novel's protagonist visits a grave near Brocklebridge Church fifteen years after her friend dies at Lowood School. This novel's protagonist is locked up as a child by Sarah Reed and comforts her future husband after Grace Poole's charge, (*) Bertha Mason, burns down Thornfield Hall. For ten points, name this Charlotte Bronte \u0308 novel in which the title woman marries Mr Rochester.", "answer": "Jane Eyre", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jane Eyre</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Jane Eyre", "Jane Eyre"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Well of Urd is one of three wells under this object, which is tended by the Norns. This object is ironically called \"Odin's horse,\" and is home to Ratatoskr, a squirrel that carries messages between Nidhogg and an eagle who perches in the (*) branches of this tree. For ten points, identify this enormous ash that stretches between the worlds of Norse mythology.", "answer": "Yggdrasil (accept World Tree before \"world\" is read)", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Yggdrasil</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Yggdrasil", "Yggdrasil"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept World Tree before \"world\" is read"}, {"question": "This event may have happened to make room for the Domus Aurea. This event was blamed on early Christians, leading to their 64 CE persecution. According to Tacitus, this event began near the Palatine Hill while the (*) emperor was in Antium. For ten points, name this disaster that destroyed a prosperous Italian city, legendarily while Nero either played a lyre or fiddled.", "answer": "Great Fire of Rome (accept descriptions like Rome burning)", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Great Fire of Rome</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Great Fire of Rome", "Great Fire of Rome"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept descriptions like Rome burning"}, {"question": "George Gamow described this process via quantum tunneling. This behavior is exhibited by the first artificially-produced element, technetium. A sample undergoes this process over a timeframe called a (*) half-life. A Geiger counter can detect, for ten points, what phenomenon exhibited by unstable elements like uranium, which emit alpha particles to become a different, more stable element?", "answer": "radioactivity (accept radioactive decay; accept word forms; accept alpha decay; prompt on \"decay\" before \"alpha\" is read, and accept \"decay\" after \"alpha\" is read)", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>radioactivity</u></b>", "acceptable": ["radioactivity", "radioactivity"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept radioactive decay; accept word forms; accept alpha decay; prompt on \"decay\" before \"alpha\" is read, and accept \"decay\" after \"alpha\" is read"}, {"question": "A team in this city drafted Alge Crumpler, and this city's NFL team lost a 2016 draft pick for piping in fake crowd noise at their home games. This city is building SunTrust Park in Cumberland for its baseball team, which spent 20 years in (*) Turner Field. Freddie Freeman plays first base and Matt Ryan quarterbacks in, for ten points, what city, home to the Falcons and Braves and the 1996 Summer Olympics in the South?", "answer": "Atlanta", "category": "Trash", "subcategory": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Atlanta</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Atlanta", "Atlanta"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Pieter Bruegel made a painting of this type with the Fall of Icarus. The Barbizon school specialized in these paintings, like Millet's The Gleaners. John Constable painted these works in Dedham (*) Vale, including one of a hay wain by the river Stour. For ten points, name this style of painting, which feature wide views of forests, valleys, and other natural scenery.", "answer": "landscape", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>landscape</u></b>", "acceptable": ["landscape", "landscape"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This body of water is home to Antelope Island, which becomes Antelope Peninsula when the water level dips too low. This body of water lies in what was, 30,000 years ago, Lake Bonneville. This body of water has no river outflows and only loses water via evaporation, causing its high (*) salinity. This body of water lies just west of Brigham City and northwest of a namesake state capital. For ten points, name this largest body of water in Utah.", "answer": "Great Salt Lake (accept Salt Lake City after \"capital\" is read)", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Great Salt Lake</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Great Salt Lake", "Great Salt Lake"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Salt Lake City after \"capital\" is read"}, {"question": "In one of this author's novels, Luke Castellan and Thalia Grace take in Annabeth Chase. This author's novel The Son of Sobek links several of his other works, including a series about the adventures of (*) Carter and Sadie, a series about Magnus Chase, and a series beginning with The Lightning Thief. For ten points, name this author of the mythology-inspired Kane Chronicles and Percy Jackson novel series.", "answer": "Richard Russell \"Rick\" Riordan", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "Richard Russell \"Rick\" <b><u>Riordan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Richard Russell \"Rick\" Riordan", "Riordan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Because this quantity is conserved, perpetual motion machines of the first kind cannot exist. A capacitor stores this quantity in an electric field between its plates. The SI unit for this quantity describes the work done when a force of one (*) newton moves an object one meter. For ten points, name this physical quantity that is measured in Joules and comes in kinetic and potential forms.", "answer": "energy", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>energy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["energy", "energy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This current Chair of the Committee on Armed Services was shot down in 1967, then spent over five years in Hoa Lo, nicknamed the \"Hanoi Hilton.\" At one campaign stop, this man was booed for correcting an audience member who called his opponent, (*) Barack Obama, an Arab. For ten points, name this former prisoner of war during the Vietnam War, who has served five terms as Senator from Arizona.", "answer": "John Sidney McCain III", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Sidney McCain III</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Sidney McCain III", "John Sidney McCain III"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the first of the Three Woes of Revelation, these creatures appeared with scorpions' tails and the power to torment nonbelievers for five months. With wild honey, these animals made up the diet of John the Baptist. These animals (*) \"darkened the land\" after being called down by Moses, and consumed every growing plant in Egypt. For ten points, name this winged family of grasshoppers known for swarming on crops.", "answer": "locusts (accept Acrididae or Acrididaes; accept akris or akrides; accept arbeh; prompt on \"grasshopper\" before it is read; prompt on \"insects\")", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>locusts</u></b>", "acceptable": ["locusts", "locusts"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Acrididae or Acrididaes; accept akris or akrides; accept arbeh; prompt on \"grasshopper\" before it is read; prompt on \"insects\""}, {"question": "In this city, a group of fascists led by Oswald Mosley clashed with police in the Battle of Cable Street. A photograph taken atop this city's Daily Mail building was titled \"St. Paul's Survives.\" A speaker in this city claimed \"we shall defend our (*) Island, whatever the cost may be.\" Winston Churchill declared \"we shall fight on the beaches\" in, for ten points, what city's House of Commons, in the Parliament of the United Kingdom?", "answer": "London, England", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>London, England</u></b>", "acceptable": ["London, England", "London, England"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Odd numbers are multiplied by this value then added to one in the Collatz conjecture's computation. This value is the smallest Mersenne prime and the second triangular number. An integer is divisible by this value if the (*) sum of its digits is also divisible by this number. This value follows 1, 1, 2 in the Fibonacci sequence. For ten points, name this smallest odd prime number.", "answer": "three", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>three</u></b>", "acceptable": ["three", "three"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This character is introduced by Stamford, and discovers that the mysterious Red Headed League is a cover for a plot to rob a bank. This character apparently dies in a scuffle at the (*) Reichenbach Falls with his nemesis, Professor Moriarty. For ten points, name this detective created by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, who resides at 221B Baker Street with John Watson.", "answer": "Sherlock Holmes (accept either underlined name)", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sherlock Holmes</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sherlock Holmes", "Sherlock Holmes"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept either underlined name"}], "bonuses": []}